Guide to the Manly Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Manly Family Papers
1888-1976
RG 82
Yale University Divinity School Library
4
(8 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, photographs, and collected materials document the life and work of the Manly family in China. Political unrest in Chengdu 1911-1912 is well documented, as is the daily work of a Methodist missionary working with native churches. The collection includes valuable photographs of Sichuan from the early 1900s. Wilson Edward Manly, his wife Florence and daughters Marian and Grace were American Methodist missionaries in Sichuan (Szechwan) province from 1893 to 1943.
Manly family
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marian Manly, 1971
Biographical / Historical
1893 Wilson Edward Manly went to China as Methodist missionary
1896 Wilson Edward ("Ward") Manly and Florence Brown married in Shanghai, moved to Chengdu
1898 Daughter Marian born in Chungking; Marian returned to China as medical doctor; she was also an author using the pseudonym Han Suyin.
1901 Daughter Grace born in Chungking; returned to China as missionary; died in 1942.
1908 Son Gordon born in Chengdu
1913 W.E. Manly received D.D. from Cornell College
Scope and Contents
Series I, Correspondence, includes detailed original letters written by W. E. Manly to his family in the U.S. from 1911 to 1914. A political uprising in Chengdu, dealings with native teachers and churches, and Methodist mission politics are described. Correspondence with Bishop J. W. Bashford,Joseph Beech, and other missionaries relates to the political unrest. Circular letters written by the Manlys to supporters in the U.S. provide a good overview of their work. A set of excerpts from Manly correspondence called "Chronicles" provides a glimpse of correspondence early than the letters available in original format.
Series II, Writings, includes material written by W. E. Manly, Grace Manly, and Marian Manly. W. E. Manly was interested in engineering devices to improve life in West China, including a waterwheel system to produce electricity. An essay by Marian Manly describes the Chin I School of Midwifery, which she headed.
Series III, Photographs, includes portraits and group shots of missionaries, Chinese native workers, conferences, and school groups, as well as scenery and scenes from life in Sichuan province in the early 1900s. Many of the photographs are identified, with approximate dates.
Series IV, Collected Material and Memorabilia, includes ephemeral written material and artifacts.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings
III. Photographs
IV. Collected Items and Memorabilia
Missions -- China; China -- History -- Boxer Rebellion, 1899-1901; Clergy; Missionaries; Manly, Florence; Manly, Grace; Manly, Marian; Manly, Wilson E.; Methodist Episcopal Church
- Correspondence, Series I
  - W.E. Manly from Chungking, Tzechow, and elsewhere in Sichuan to family in Ohio, incl. re. Methodist conference, 1893, 1911 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - W.E. Manly from Tzechow, Chungking, and elsewhere to family, incl. re. Bible School, trips to outlying congregations, political unrest in Chentu, Pa Gao secret society, 1911 Jul - Dec (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - W.E. Manly from Tzechow and elsewhere to family, incl. re. robberies, railroads, 1912 Jan - Jun (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - W.E. Manly from Tzechow and elsewhere to family, incl. re. trips to countryside, electrical power, "white slavery", 1912 Jul - Dec (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - W.E. Manly from Tzechow and elsewhere to family, incl. re. salaries of native pastors, mission property, 1913 Jan - Jun (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - W.E. Manly from Tzechow and elsewhere to family; incl. re. native teacher playing cards, political unrest in Chungking, 1913 Jul - Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - W.E. Manly from Tzechow and elsewhere to family, incl. re. statistics of converts; return home on furlough (1914); return to China with Florence and Gordon, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - WEM to siblings and father, 1911-1915 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - WEM to others, incl. Bishop J. W. Bashford, Joseph Beech, J. E. Johnson, re. insurrection in Yang Shien and Chentu, mission finances, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Florence Manly to WEM and daughters, 1911, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Chronicles" - excerpts from letters, 1892-1895 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Chronicles" - excerpts from letters, 1896-1900 (Box 1, Folder 11a)
  - Circular letters to "Friends of the Decatur District," "Friends," incl. re.political unrest, 1911-1915 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - To/from WEM: American Consular Service, incl. re. political unrest, 1911, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - To WEM: Bashford, Beech, Alice Brethorst, incl. re. "Revolutionists", 1911 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters from others to WEM: Cornell College re. DD conferred on WEM in absentia, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - To/fromWEM: T. James, Spencer Lewis, S. McCartney, E. Meuser, J. Nicolson, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - To/from WEM: H. Openshaw, C. B. Rape, J. Sparling, Thomas Torrance, 1911, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters from others to Florence Manly, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Marian Manly to/from family, 1952, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Marian Manly to/from others, incl. to Sen. Fulbright, to President Nixon re. Vietnam War, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Joseph Beech to Bp. Bashford re.uprising in Chentu, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Cables; inventory of correspondence prepared by Marian Manly, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Writings, Series II
  - Of W.E. Manly
    - News updates re. political situation, etc., 1911-1913 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Re. Railroad and power sites, 1911-1912 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Reports re. mission work, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "A Visit to the Salt Wells"; "Thoughts on Homegoing", 1911, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Of Grace Manly
    - Re. Missionary service, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Of Marian Manly
    - Re. Chin I School of Midwifery, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Notes, Talks (Box 2, Folder 28a)
- Photographs, Series III
  - Portraits and family groups: W.E. and Florence, early 1900s (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Portraits and family groups: W.E. and Florence in groups (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Portraits and family groups: Grace and Marian (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Portraits and family groups: ancestors (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Chinese students and other associates (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Chinese students and other associates (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Chinese students and other associates (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Chinese students and other associates (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Chinese students and other associates, early 1900s - 1950 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Chinese associates, incl. native pastors and families (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Methodist missionaries in West China; China Inland Mission missionaries in Chinese clothing (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Missionaries (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Missionaries; incl. vacationing in Szechuan (Sichuan), travel in countryside, 1906-1947 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Methodist women missionaries (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Missionaries of other missions - Szechuan (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Methodist Bishops (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Spencer Lewis (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Methodist Annual Conferences, school groups, 1897-1937 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Conference groups, 1908-1940s (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Church groups (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Mission school groups, 1906-1930s (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Chinese individuals and groups (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Missionaries and Chinese workers (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Missionaries and Chinese workers - tribes country ("Thibetans") (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Various mission projects, incl. babies born at Chin I School of Midwifery, native pastors (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Chengtu Methodist Church construction, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Tien Gu Chao Methodist station (destroyed by Boxers, then rebuilt), 1902 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - W. E. Manly's waterwheel project for electricity (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Tzechow - Pilgrim Festival - "Bright Eye" goddess, ca. 1907 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Tzechow - Revolution of 1912 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Szechuan scenes (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Szechuan scenes (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Szechuan scenes (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Szechuan scenes - cities, Jin Fu San (Mt. of Golden Happiness) (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Szechuan scenes - cities (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Szechuan scenes - bridges (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Szechuan scenes - temples, priests, idols (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Life of the people of Szechuan (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Life of the people of Szechuan (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Life of the people of Szechuan (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Life of the people of Szechuan (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Wen Miao Ho Gai (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Unidentified scenes - China (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Unidentified scenes - China (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Unidentified scenes - China (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Unidentified scenes - China (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Unidentified scenes - China (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Unidentified scenes - China (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Methods of travel in Szechuan (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Photos from other provinces (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - Yangtze River scenes (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Yangtze River scenes (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Yangtze River scenes (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Unidentified buildings (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Unidentified buildings (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - University of California, 1888-1900 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Misc. individuals (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Hudson Taylor, China Inland Mission missionaries, 1899 (Box 6, Folder 86)
- Collected Items and Memorabilia, Series IV
  - Newspaper clippings, 1895 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Financial statement / poem (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Silver chopsticks of Marian Manly (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - Red Cross pass (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - New Testament and Bible of Marian Manly (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Address book (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Embroidered cloths (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - Printed paper (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - Chinese plaque (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - Chinese shoes (Box 8, Folder 96)
  - Vases (Box 8, Folder 97)